A Guide to the Correspondence and Subject Files of the Virginia Secretary of Administration, 1990-1994
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Correspondence and Subject Files of the Virginia Secretary of Administration, 1990-1994
The Library of Virginia
34714
16 cu. ft. (16 boxes)
Virginia. Secretary of Administration
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was transferred July 1994 by the Office of the Secretary of Administration.
Biographical Information
The Office of Administration was established in 1966 as part of the Office of the Governor to assist the chief executive in carrying out his duties. Several agencies including the divisions of the Budget, Personnel, Engineering and Building and Planning reported to the Commissioner of Administration. This system was inadequate. In 1970, the Governor's Management Commission Study recommended the creation of six "Deputy Governors" to assist the Chief Executive in his managerial duties. Compatible functions of government were grouped under these administrative heads, who would serve as the Governors top management team or "secretariats," as they are called now.
Governor Linwood Holton's top priority for the 1972 session of the General Assembly was a proposal for a Governor's Cabinet, reorganizing state agencies into six major departments--each headed by a secretary appointed by the governor. The Office of Administration was made one of these six departments. The office of Secretary of Administration was created on April 8, 1972, by an act passed by the General Assembly. Governor Holton appointed T. Edward Temple, the Commissioner of Administration since 1970, as the first Secretary of Administration. When Temple took office on July 1, 1972, he was responsible for the divisions of the Budget, Personnel, Engineering and Buildings, Automated Data Processing, Justice and Crime Prevention, State Planning and Community Affairs, Council on the Environment, State Board of Elections and the Office of Special Programs. The Office has undergone a series of administrative reorganizations since 1972. On April 12, 1976, the Legislature combined the secretariats for administration and finance, effective July 1, 1976. On July 1, 1984, the offices were separated. The Secretary of Administration is a member of the Governor's Cabinet, and is appointed by the governor, subject to confirmation by the General Assembly. Currently, the Secretary of Administration is responsible for the direction or jurisdiction over the following state agencies and boards: Department of Charitable Gaming, Compensation Board, State Board of Elections, Department of Employment Dispute Resolution, Department of General Services, Department of Human Resource Management, Council on Human Rights, Public Broadcasting Board, and the Department of Veterans Services.
T. Edward Temple, the first Secretary of Administration, announced in August 1973 that he was leaving state service effective January 1974. In December 1973, Governor-elect Mills E. Godwin, Jr., announced the appointment of Maurice B. Rowe, III, as Secretary of Administration. Rowe had served as Secretary of Commerce and Resources in the Holton administration. On July 1, 1976, the secretariates of administration and finance were combined. Rowe served until the end of the Godwin administration in January 1978 when he became Secretary of Commerce and Resources in the Dalton administration. In December 1977 Governor-elect John N. Dalton picked Charles B. Walker, the state comptroller, as Secretary of Administration and Finance. The office wielded great influence and authority under Walker who was known as the "Little Governor". Walker resigned in June 1981 to become a vice-president for Ethyl Corporation. Stuart Connock, state budget and planning director, served as Secretary of Administration and Finance until the end of Dalton's term in January 1982.
Governor-elect Charles S. Robb, the first Democrat to be elected governor since 1965, did not retain any of Dalton's cabinet secretaries. Robb appointed Wayne F. Anderson, a former Alexandria city manager, Secretary of Administration and Finance. Anderson announced his resignation in May 1984 to join the faculty of George Mason University. His resignation was prompted by a cabinet reorganization to take effect on July 1, 1984 which divided the Secretary of Administration and Finance into separate secretariats and combined the secretariats of transportation and public safety. Governor Robb appointed Secretary of Transportation Andrew B. Fogarty as new Secretary of Administration. Fogarty served until June 1985 when he became Sectretary of Transportation and Public Safety following the resignation of Franklin E. White. David K. McCloud, Robb's chief of staff, assumed the duties of Secretary of Administration for the remainder of Robb's term.
In December 1985, Governor-elect Gerald L. Baliles chose Carolyn J. Moss, head of the Office of Minority Business Enterprise under Governor Robb, as Secretary of Administration. Moss served until the end of Baliles' term in 1990. Governor-elect L. Douglas Wilder appointed Ruby G. Martin, a Richmond attorney, as Secretary of Administration. In January 1994 Governor-elect George Allen, the first Republican elected governor since 1977, appointed his campaign manager, Michael E. Thomas, Secretary of Administration. Thomas served until the end of Allen's term in January 1998. Governor James S. Gilmore appointed Thomas Deputy Secretary of Technology in August 1998. In January 1998 Governor-elect James S. Gilmore III named G. Bryan Slater as Secretary of Administration. Slater also served as Gilmore's Deputy Chief of Staff. He worked on Gilmore's campaign for attorney general in 1993 and served as his director of administration when Gilmore was Virginia Attorney General (1994-1997). Slater resigned in March 2001 to work for the Republican National Committee which Gilmore chaired. He was replaced by his deputy, Donald L. Moseley who served until the end of the Gilmore administration in January 2002.
Governor-elect Mark R. Warner selected Sandra Bowen as Secretary of Administration in January 2002. Bowen had previously served as Special Assistant to Governor Charles S. Robb, and as Secretary of the Commonwealth during the administration of Governor Gerald L. Baliles. She was also the Director of Gubernatorial Transition between the Robb and Baliles administrations. Secretary Bowen served under Governor Warner for his entire term, and was replaced in 2006 when Governor-elect Timothy Kaine selected Viola Baskerville as his Secretary of Administration.
Scope and Content
This collection contains memorandums, briefs, project files, mass mailings and reports. Correspondants include the Governor's Office, state agencies, and department heads. Box 3 contains documents related to Viriginia's Veterans, specifically a new care facility; included are reports, newspaper clippings and photographs of the center under construction. Box 11-12 contains documents related the the Southern Governor's Association trip to Africa in 1993 which explored economic trade prospects throughout 25 countries.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I. Correspondence and Subject Files
Contents List
- Series I. Correspondence and Subject Files, 1990-1994., Extent: 16 cu. ft. (16 boxes). (Box 1-16)
  Original arrangement of the agency has been maintained, folders are generally grouped by department.
  - State Auditor's Hot Line, 1992-1993. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - State Auditor's Hot Line, 1993. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Secretary of Finance (Files from folder), 1991-1992. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Secretary of the Commonwealth, 1992-1993. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Department of General Services: Sole Source Funding, 1991-1992. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Virginia Commonwealth University: Research Park Meeting, 1993 Jan 7. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Virginia Museum of Fine Arts, 1993. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Transit Pass Program, 1993. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Virginia Railway Express Meeting, 1990. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - State Environmental Impact Reports, 1993. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Virginia Liaison Office, 1991-1992. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Office of the Leutenant Governor: General, 1992-1993. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Office of the Attorny General, 1990-1993. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Department of General Services: Proposed Regulations for the Certification of Labs Analyzing Drinking Water, 1993. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Department of General Services: Division of Forensic Science, 1990-1994. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Department of General Services: Commission for the Perservation of the Capitol, 1991. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Department of General Services: Cheatham Annex, 1991. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Department of General Services: General, 1993. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Department of General Services: Leases/Deeds/Acquisitions 1990-1994. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Department of General Services: Library Site Selection, 1991. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Department of General Services: Handicap Alterations at the Capitol 1991. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Department of General Services: Parking Increase Issue Meeting, 1993 Jan 25. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Department of General Services: Parking, 1991. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Department of General Services: Space Request 1990. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Department of General Services: Surplus Property 1990-1991. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Department of General Services: Purchase and Supply - General, 1990-1994. (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Department of General Services: Minority Procurement, 1991. (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Department of Veterans Affairs, 1991-1993. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Virginia Veterans Care Center, 1992. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Virginia Veterans Care Center, 1991. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Department of Personnel and Training, 1990-1994. (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Department of Personnel and Training: Classification and Compensation, 1990-1994. (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Department of Personnel and Training: Equal Employment Opportunity, 1990-1994. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Flexible Spending Accounts, 1990-1994. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Department of Personnel and Training, 1990-1994. (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Virginia Retirement Systems, 1991-1992. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Virginia Retirement Systems: Financial Statements, 1990-1994. (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Virginia Retirement Systems: Optional Retirement Plans, 1990-1991. (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Department of Personnel and Training: Disaster Relief Training, 1991-1992. (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Department of Personnel and Training: Alcohol and Other Drugs Policy, 1991. (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Department of Personnel and Training: Employee Recognition Programs, 1991. (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Department of Personnel and Training: Employee Volunteer Time for Schools, 1991-1993. (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Department of Personnel and Training: evaluating Agency Heads, 1991. (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Department of Personnel and Training: Paid Military Leave, 1991. (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Department of Personnel and Training: Parental Leave, 1991. (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Department of Personnel and Training: Sexual Harassment, 1990-1992. (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Department of Personnel and Training: Inclement Weather Policy, 1991-1992. (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Department of Personnel and Training: Leave Sharing, 1990-1993. (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Department of Personnel and Training: Smoking Policy, 1990. (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Department of Personnel and Training: Acting Pay Policy, 1991-1993. (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Department of Personnel and Training: Yuletide Policy, 1990-1993. (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Department of Personnel and Training: Policies, 1991-1992. (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Project Strealine phase II, 1991-1992. (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Department of Personnel and Training, 1990-1993. (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Department of General Services: Mapping, 1990-1991. (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Department of General Services: Virginia Commonwealth University - Master Plan, 1990. (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Agency Head Appointments, 1991-1993. (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Downsizing and Consolidation, 1991-1992. (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Cabinet Meetings, 1990-1993. (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Excerpts from Governor Wilders, 1991-1993. (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - General Correspondence, 1993. (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Internal Service Funds, 1991. (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Legislation, 1991-1994. (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Memorandums to Agency Heads and Institutions of Higher Learning, 1991-1993. (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Memorandums to Governor's Cabinet, 1991-1993. (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Memorandums to and from the Governor's Office, 1991-1993. (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Children's Defense Fund: "Mickey's Worldwide Kids Party", 1993. (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Joint Legislative Audit Review Commission: Publication Study, 1991. (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Security, 1990. (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Division of Selected Agencies, 1992-1993. (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Severance Pay for Gubnertorial Appointees, 1993. (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Department of General Services: Risk Management, 1990-1992. (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Department of General Services: Risk Management - Self-Insurance Workers Compensaion, 1990-1992. (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Human Rights, 1991-1993. (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Council on Information Management, 1992-1993. (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Commission on Local Government, 1991-1992. (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Compensation Board, 1990-1991. (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - State Board of Elections, 1991. (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Department of Employee Relations Councelors, 1990-1993. (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Department of General Services, 1991-1993. (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Department of General Services, 1993. (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Virginia War Memorial, 1992-1993. (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Virginia War Memorial Meeting, 1992 May 27. (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Virginia War Memorial, 1990-1991. (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Compensation Board - Jail, 1989-1990. (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Department of Employee Relations Counselors, 1990. (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Intellectual Property, 1990-1992. (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Sole Source Purchases, 1993. (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Veterans Care Center, 1990. (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Early Retirement, 1991. (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Southern Governor's Association/African Heads of State Summit Materials, 1993. (Box 11, Folder 1-4)
  - Hosts/Hostesses Staffing Schedules, 1993. (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - African Heads of State Summit, 1993. (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - African African-American Summit, 1993. (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - African Heads of State - Briefing Book, 1993. (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Africa Briefing Materials, 1993. (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Africa Briefing Materials, 1993. (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Africa Briefing Materials, 1993. (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Information Packets Submitted by African Nations, 1993. (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Summit Correspondence, 1993. (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Focus Groups/Tours, 1993. (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Post Summit, 1993. (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Business Invitees, 1993. (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Invitees - Domestic or otherwise, 1993. (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - Focus Groups/Tours/Parallel and Post Programs, 1993. (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - Registration Information, 1993. (Box 12, Folder 15)
  - Slavery Museum Correspondence, 1993-1994. (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Slavery Museum Correspondence, 1993-1994. (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Governor's Trade Mission to Africa: Briefing Book, 1992. (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - African Trade and Cultural Mission, 1992. (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Trade Mission Booklet: Pine Tree Press, 1992. (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Department of Information Technology, 1990-1993. (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Department of Information Technology - Financial Statements, 1990-1993. (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Department of Information Technology - General, 1991-1993. (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Department of Information Technology - Procurement, 1991-1993. (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Department of Information Technology - Public Telecommunications Board, 1991. (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Department of Information Technology, 1990-1993. (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Virginia Military Adisory Council, 1991. (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - U.S. Army Corps of Engineers - Activities in Virginia, 1991. (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Actions Against Violent Crime, 1993. (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Governor's Drug Control Strategy, 1991. (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Public Safety, 1991-1993. (Box 15, Folders 5-8)
  - Report ot the Sate Corporation Commission, 1990. (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - No-Fault Automobile Insurance, 1991. (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - Public Safety/Policy, 1993. (Box 15, Folder 11)
  - Public Safety - Correspondnece, 1993. (Box 15, Folder 12)
  - Council on Forgeign Relations, 1991. (Box 15, Folder 13)
  - Drug Control Strategy, 1991. (Box 15, Folder 14)
  - Base Closings, 1993. (Box 15, Folder 15)
  - Gun Control, 1993. (Box 15, Folder 16)
  - Drunk Driving Vote Sheet, 1993. (Box 15, Folder 17)
  - Secretary of Transportation - Milliken, 1991. (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Secretary of Transportation - Policy, 1993. (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Secretary of Transportation - Milliken: Capitol Outlay, 1991. (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Secretary of Transportation - Milliken, 1991. (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Secretary of Transportation - Metropolitan Washington Airport Authority, 1993. (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Secretary of Transportation - Review of Transportation Study, 1992. (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Secretary of Transportation - Dulles and National: Washington's Airports, 1991. (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Transportation, 1992. (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - Administrative Fees Collected, 1991. (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - Transkei Visit, 1991 Oct 5-9. (Box 16, Folder 10)